Module 14 Ethics and Professional
Responsibility, module overview.
For many years, project management was not
considered a profession.
And in fact, many people today still think
it's not a profession.
The main reason for this is that many
on-train people manage a piece of work to
completion and then start calling
themselves a project manager.
This is like looking after your
Aunt Jemima when she has
the flu, and then calling
yourself a doctor or a surgeon.
However, there are a couple of things that
sets a profession apart
from an ordinary job.
And these things would include that a
profession has entry requirements,
education, special training,
certification, a body of knowledge,
which we call a book, and a code of
ethics.
On this course, we've covered the body of
knowledge, PIMBOC, and you have the
education training for your job and you're
probably studying towards your PMP
certification and now in this module we're
covering the code of ethics and
professional conduct which all adds up to
the professional project management what
we will cover in this module 14.0 ethics
and professional responsibility module
overview which is this video 14.1
responsibility responsibility,
14.2, respect, 14.3, fairness and 14.4,
honesty.
First of all, we will examine
the vision and applicability, 1.
1, vision and purpose.
As practitioners of project
management, we are
committed to doing what
is right and honourable.
We set high standards for ourselves and
aspire to meet those standards in all
aspects of our lives, at work, at home,
and in the service of her profession.
Remembering that this is not from the
PIMBOC guide, and though this is
examinable material, this is from a
separate document called the PMI Code of
Ethics and Professional Contact, which you
can download free from the PMI website.
And did you notice that we are called to
be ethical in all aspects of our lives,
at work and at home?
That means if we're not managing projects
and even when we're not at work,
as long as we are in any way connected
with PMI, the Project Management
Institute, we must aspire to meet those
standards.
It goes on to say this code of ethics and
professional conduct describes the
expectations that we have
of ourselves on our fellow
practitioners in the global
project management community.
Now, did you notice that it says it's not
just ourselves, we have to watch out for
our fellow practitioners in the global
project management community is to make
sure that they are behaving ethically as
well.
However, we do not have to obey the whole
code.
Certain codes we must obey.
Some of these codes are not mandatory,
but we should still aspire to obey them.
The code says it articulates the ideals to
which we aspire as well as the behaviours
that are mandatory in our professional and
volunteer roles.
The purpose of this code is to instill
confidence in the project management
profession and to help an individual
become a better practitioner.
It says instill confidence in the project
management profession.
Every time a project manager acts
unethically or someone related with the
PMI or someone who has a
PMP, if they act unethically,
the profession of project
managers as a whole suffers.
And that is why we must aspire to meet
these standards.
Because when we do, we help not just our
profession, but also our fellow
practitioners and ultimately the whole
community.
How do we do this?
We do this by establishing
a profession-wide
understanding of appropriate behaviour.
We believe that the credibility and
reputation of the project management
profession is shaped by the collective
conduct of individual practitioners.
We believe that we can advance our
profession both individually and
collectively by embracing this code of
ethics and professional conduct.
Understanding the PMI Code of Ethics and
Professional Conduct gives us an
understanding of the type of behaviour
which is appropriate.
We also believe this code will assist us
in making wise decisions, particularly
when faced with difficult
situations where we may
be asked to compromise
our integrity or our values.
Our hope is that this Code of
Ethics and Professional Conduct
will serve as a catalyst
for others to study delivery.
deliberate and write about ethics and
values.
Further, we hope this
code will ultimately be
used to build upon and
evolve our profession.
This code reduces the guesswork when we're
faced with an ethical dilemma and provides
us with the framework for making the right
decisions and moving forward.
1.2.
Persons to whom the code applies.
Spoiler alert, the code of ethics and
professional conduct applies to everybody
in any any way connected with PMI
whatsoever.
It says it applies to all PMI members.
And so if you're a member of PMI,
you don't need to look any further in this
chapter to find out if you have to follow
the code.
The simple answer is yes you do.
Okay but what if you aren't a PMI member?
Individuals are not members of PMI but
meet one or more of the following criteria.
non-members who hold a PMI certification.
And that's something that many people
don't actually realise that you don't have
to be a member of PMI to have a PMP
certification.
I would strongly recommend that you remain
a member of PMI.
I've been a member of PMI for over 20
years.
But unfortunately, in some countries,
the amount of money they earn is quite,
minuscule compared with
developed countries and
they just can't afford to
pay the PMI membership.
Personally I find the PMI membership is
very reasonable cost compared with some of
my other memberships and I get a lot of
value for PMI membership.
Non-members who apply to commence a PMI
certification process.
So from the instant that
you hit the button to apply to
begin a certification process,
you are bound by the code.
Non-members who serve PMI in a volunteer
capacity.
Now that we know who the
code applies to and some
of its benefits, let's
consider hard structured.
1.3 structure of the code.
The Code of Ethics and Professional
Conduct comprises for values of PMI have
identified as most important to the
project management community and these are
responsibility, respect fairness and
honesty and the code is divided into four
main sections with one section for each of
these codes each section explains the
value and it lists three separate things
for each one a description of the value to
the aspirational standards i.e the
standards which are not compulsory but you
can't consider them
optional either you must try
your absolute best to
aspire to these standards.
And number three,
mandatory standards, i .e., the
rules concerning the
value that you must obey.
There's no choice about these.
If you do not obey these rules, then by
definition, you are not behaving ethically.
Practitioners who do not conduct
themselves in accordance with the
mandatory standards will be subject to
disciplinary procedures
before PMI's ethics review.
You can have your PMP certificate removed,
for example.
You can even be banned from if we're
taking another PMP exam.
For notes that are not part of the
mandatory or aspirational standards,
these appear on the code.
They're there to provide examples and
other clarifications.
I'll just point out one thing which I
noticed is that some of the notes are
written in pale grey on top
of slightly darker grey and
it's easy to miss them so
look carefully for those notes.
Finally a glossary can be found at the end
of the standard.
Glossary defines words and phrases used in
the code and you will find that each time
a word which appears in a
glossary appears from the
first time in the text it will
be underlined in the text.
So if you see an underlined
word it means it appears in the
glossary but it's not going
to be underlined after that.
Section 4 values that support this code.
Practitioners from the global project
management community were asked to
identify the values
that formed the basis of
their decision-making
and guided directions.
The values that the global project
management community defined as most
important were responsibility,
respect, fairness and honesty.
This code affirms these four values as its
foundation.
Comment.
The conduct covered under the aspirational
standards and conduct covered under the
mandatory standards are not mutually
exclusive.
That is, one specific
act or a mission could
violate both aspirational
and mandatory standards.
And that brings us to
the end of Ethics and
Professional Responsibility
Module Overview.
The next lesson is 14.1.
Responsibility.
Please read the Code
of Ethics and Professional
Responsibility before
reading this section.